(ﾋﾛｼ)７月20日 今日から
ｽﾍﾟｰｽあさがおの観察日記を始める｡
July 20th.
Today, I'll be starting an observation journal
on a space morning glory today.
ﾎﾞｸは あさがおが早く咲くように
いっぱい 水をあげました｡
I gave it lots of water so the morning
glory would bloom faster.
まだかな？ いつになったら
あさがおと会えるかな？
How much longer?
When will I get to see the morning glory?
７月25日 朝 起きたら
あさがおが芽を出していました｡
July 25th.
I woke up to find that the morning
glory had sprouted.
はじめまして あさがおさん｡
Nice to meet you, Mr. Morning Glory.
ﾎﾞｸは 嬉しくて
いっぱい 水をあげました｡
I was so happy,
I gave it lots of water.
And then Mom got mad at me.
そしたら お母さんに➡
She said the morning
glory was already full.
もう あさがおはお腹いっぱいだよ
って 怒られました｡
８月11日
台風が 江戸を直撃しました｡
August 11th.
A typhoon hit Edo.
ﾎﾞｸは
あさがおが飛ばされないように➡
I stayed with the morning glory the whole
time so it wouldn't be blown away.
ずっと 一緒にいました｡
そしたら お母さんにｶｾﾞをひくって
すごく怒られました｡
And then Mom got really mad at me.
She said I would catch a cold.
But I was worried so I ignored her,
でも ぼくは心配だから➡
無視したら
お母さんと ｹﾝｶになりました｡
and then Mom and I got into a fight.
８月12日 雨は まだ やみません｡
August 12th.
It was still raining.
ﾎﾞｸは 熱が出て ずっと寝てました｡
I was in bed all day with a fever.
何度も あさがおを
見に行こうとしたけど➡
I kept trying to go check
on the morning glory,
お母さんが
行かせてくれませんでした｡
but Mom wouldn't let me go.
お母さんは あさがおが
どうなってもいいんだ｡
Mom didn't care what happened
to the morning glory.
ﾎﾞｸは もう
お母さんと口をきかない｡
I'm never gonna talk to Mom again...
８月13日 朝 起きたら
あさがおが なくなっていました｡
August 13th.
I woke up to find that the
morning glory was gone.
ﾎﾞｸが行ってあげれば
あさがおは 死ななかったのに…｡
The morning glory wouldn't have
died if I had stayed with it.
ごめんなさい ごめんなさい｡
I'm sorry. I'm sorry...
ﾎﾞｸが泣いていると お母さんが➡
I was crying, when Mom brought a
fully-bloomed morning glory in a pot.
鉢に咲いた あさがおを
持ってきました｡
Mom had moved the morning glory
to a pot during the typhoon for me.
お母さんは 台風の中 あさがおを
鉢に移してくれていました｡
ﾎﾞｸの代わりに
友達を守ってくれました｡
She protected my friend in my place.
ごめんなさい ごめんなさい｡
I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
結局 ﾎﾞｸは泣きました｡
I still ended up crying.
But it wasn't because I was sad,
it was because I was happy.
でも この涙は 悲しいのじゃなく
嬉しい涙でした｡
８月30日 お母さんと一緒に
あさがおに水をあげました｡
August 30th.
I watered the morning glory with Mom.
あさがおは 今日も
たくましく育っています｡ 終わり｡
The morning glory is still growing strong.
[Independent Research Project Presentation]
The end.
(先生)はい ﾋﾛｼ君 ありがとう｡
あさがお 枯れなくて よかったね｡
Okay, thank you, Hiroshi-kun.
It's nice that the morning glory didn't die.
Great!
お母さんとも仲直りできたし…｡
And you made up with your mother.
え～ ﾋﾛｼ君の気持が
よく伝わってくる➡
Yes, a very well written report which
conveyed Hiroshi-kun's feelings.
たいへん よくできた
研究文でした｡
え～っと じゃあ 次は…｡
Then next up is...
大五郎君｡
(大五郎)はい｡
Daigoro-kun.
Yes.
大五郎君は 夏休み
いったい 何を研究したのかな？
Daigoro-kun, what did you
research this summer?
え～っと… ﾎﾞ… ﾎﾞｸも
観察日記をつけてきました｡
Uh...
I also did an observation journal.
そうですか｡
いったい 何を観察したのかな？
I see. What did you observe?
楽しみだね みんな｡ それじゃ
大五郎君 いってみようか｡
Isn't everybody excited?
Well, Daigoro-kun, go ahead.
３年１組 北大路大五郎｡
Class 3-1, Daigoro Kitaouji.
７月20日 今日から
待ちに待った夏休みです｡
July 20th.
Today is the first day of my
long-awaited summer vacation.
明日から何をして遊ぼうか？
How shall I have fun tomorrow?
そんなことを寝る前から考えて
わくわくしてたら➡
I was so excited that I couldn't fall asleep
ﾗｼﾞｵ体操に遅れました｡
and missed my radio exercises.
ｺﾗ 大五郎君！
１日目から ﾗｼﾞｵ体操 ｻﾎﾞったの？
Hey, Daigoro-kun!
You skipped radio exercises
on the very first day?
ﾀﾞﾒじゃないか！
That's no good.
公園に行ったら
もう誰もいませんでした｡ でも…｡
By the time I got to the park,
nobody was there.
But...
(長谷川)さ… 酒…｡
S-Sake...
た… 頼む！ さ… 酒をくれ！
P-Please...
G-Give me sake!
(大五郎)そこで ﾎﾞｸは
ﾏﾀﾞｵと出会いました｡
That was where I met Madao.
あの… ﾏﾀﾞｵって 何？
Uh...
What's a Madao?
["An Observation Journal Should
Be Seen Through To The Very End"]
July 21st.
I started an observation
journal on Madao today.
(大五郎)今日から ﾏﾀﾞｵの
観察日記をつけることにしました｡
(先生)大五郎君 ちょっと待って｡
ﾏﾀﾞｵって 何？ ねぇ！
Daigoro-kun, hold on.
What's a Madao?
Madao is the master of the park.
(大五郎)ﾏﾀﾞｵは 公園のぬしです｡
ﾋｹﾞの生えた ｸﾞﾗｻﾝの生きもので➡
A creature with a beard and sunglasses.
基本 一日中
働かずに公園でじっとしています｡
It sits in the park all day without working.
Daigoro-kun, that's just a
middle-aged man, yes?
大五郎君 それ
ただのｵｯｻﾝだよね？
公園に住んでる
ただの 無職のｵｯｻﾝだよね!?
An unemployed middle-aged
man living in the park, yes?!
昨日 お酒を家から持ってきたら➡
I brought him alcohol from my house yesterday,
and he warmed up and started talking to me.
なついて
喋ってくるようになりました｡
(先生)いや ﾀﾞﾒだって そんなもの
あげたら！ 知らないおじさんに｡
You shouldn't give stuff like
that to a strange old man!
坊主 酒は？
Kid, where's the sake?
お酒がないと生きられない
と言うので➡
He said that he can't live without sake,
ﾎﾞｸは いっぱい
ﾏﾀﾞｵにお酒をあげました｡
so I gave Madao lots of sake.
まだかな…｡
How much longer?
When will Madao bloom?
いつになったら
ﾏﾀﾞｵは咲くんだろう｡
咲かないよ！
It won't!
そんなもん あげてるかぎり
永遠に咲かないよ そのｵｯｻﾝ！
As long as you keep giving him sake,
that old man will never bloom!
July 22nd.
Madao still hasn't sprouted.
ﾏﾀﾞｵは まだ芽が出ない｡
Sprouted?
(先生)芽が出ないって…
大の大人に➡
You shouldn't say that about
a grown man, Daigoro-kun.
それは ないんじゃないかな
大五郎君｡
I give it lots of sake but
it won't move or work.
(大五郎)いくら お酒をあげても
動きも働きもしません｡
なんで 何もしないの？
って聞いたら…｡
I ask why it won't do anything...
一度枯れた花は
二度と咲かねぇんだよ…｡
Once a flower's withered,
it can never bloom again.
He answered me with a
sad look on his face.
(大五郎)悲しそうな目で
そう言ってました｡
何 これ！ なんの研究!?
子供に なんてこと言ってんの！
What is this?! What kind
of project is this?!
How can he say such things to a child?!
July 23rd.
Madao still hasn't sprouted.
(大五郎)ﾏﾀﾞｵは まだ芽が出ない｡
いくら お酒をあげても
目から 全部流してしまいます｡
I give it lots of sake but it
all comes out of its eyes.
どうして せっかくあげたのに
流しちゃうの？ って聞いたら…｡
I ask why it spills back out
after I give it to him...
ごめんね… もう 流さないから｡
ごめんね｡
I'm sorry...
I won't waste any more...
And then more sake came from its eyes.
そう言って また
目から お酒を流していました｡
日が暮れるまで ずっと…｡
(先生)大五郎君？
Until the sunset.
Say, Daigoro-kun?
ちょっと 重たいね… ねぇ｡
何 これ？ もう やめない？
This is a little heavy, yeah? Yeah?
What is this? Could you stop?
July 24th.
(大五郎)ﾏﾀﾞｵは まだ 芽が出ない｡
(先生)大五郎君 わかった！
Madao still hasn't sprouted.
Daigoro-kun, I get it now.
You skipped your independent
research project, didn't you?
ﾎﾝﾄは 自由研究
さぼって やってないんでしょ！
(大五郎)ﾏﾀﾞｵは 何か
ｹｶﾞをしているようなので➡
Madao looked hurt.
That's it. Madao doesn't even exist.
どうしたの？ って聞くと…｡
I ask what's wrong...
ﾌﾞﾗﾝｺを作ろうとして
失敗した と言っていました｡
And it says that it screwed
up while making a swing.
(先生)大五郎君!!
(大五郎)ﾎﾞｸは どうして➡
Daigoro-kun!!
I ask why it's using a rope to make a swing
when the park already has swings.
とっくに 公園に ﾌﾞﾗﾝｺがあるのに
縄で ﾌﾞﾗﾝｺなんか作るんだろうと➡
不思議でした｡ いつになったら
ﾏﾀﾞｵは咲くんだろう…｡
When will Madao bloom?
(先生)大五郎君 これ
まずいことになってるから！
Daigoro-kun, I don't like
where this is going!
Are you sure about this?!
大丈夫なの!? これ！
July 25th.
Madao still hasn't sprouted.
(大五郎)ﾏﾀﾞｵは まだ芽が出ない｡
I was on my way to do radio exercises when
I found Madao lying on the rail tracks.
ﾗｼﾞｵ体操に向かう途中
ﾏﾀﾞｵが線路で寝てました｡
I ask what's it's doing,
何をやってるのか と聞くと
寝苦しくて ここまで➡
and it says it couldn't fall asleep
so it crawled over here.
転がってきてしまった と
言っていました｡
Whoa!
Stop it!
いつになったら
ﾏﾀﾞｵは咲くんだろう…｡
When will Madao bloom?
That's enough, Daigoro-kun!
発表 終わり！
よくできてましたね～｡
Report over.
An excellent job.
途中までですが もう 結構です｡
(子供たち)え～っ！
You aren't finished, but that's enough.
Why, Teacher?
なんで？ 先生！
もっと聞きたい！
I wanna hear more!
ﾏﾀﾞｵは咲いたの？
どうなったの？
Did Madao bloom?
What happened?
It's not about it blooming or not.
いや… 咲いた とか
そういう あれじゃ…｡
続き！ 続きが聞きたい！
最後まで読めよ 大五郎！
More! I wanna hear more!
Finish the story, Daigoro!
(子供たち)ﾏﾀﾞｵ！ ﾏﾀﾞｵ！
Madao! Madao!
Madao! Madao! Madao! Madao!
《いったい 何が
子供たちの心を…》
Wh-What part of that touched
the hearts of the kids...?
わ… わかりました！
じゃあ ちょっと長いようだから➡
I-I got it now!
Th-Then since it seems like your report
is rather long, we'll go with a summary.
多少 かいつまんで
やりましょうか｡
大五郎君 ８月… ８月から｡
要点だけ押さえて 読もうか｡
Daigoro-kun, August.
Start from August.
Only read the important points, okay?
あんま変なところは
かいつまんで｡
Skip the weird parts.
August 1st.
(大五郎)家族が１人増えた｡
We have a new family member.
You skipped too much!!
かいつまみすぎだろ！ なんで
ﾏﾀﾞｵが 家族の一員になってんの!?
How did Madao become a
member of your family?!
たった数日のうちに
いったい 何があったの!?
What happened in the days
that were skipped?!
(大五郎)寝床を用意してやったが
相も変わらず➡
A bed was prepared, but Madao
still hasn't sprouted.
ﾏﾀﾞｵは芽が出なかった｡
Two dry eyes stare into the empty
sky, unable to perceive...
じっと虚空を見つめるだけの
その乾いた双眸からは➡
何も 窺い知ることはできない｡
地に堕ちた堕天使ﾙｼﾌｧｰの意を➡
Much as God was unable to understand
the will of the fallen angel Lucifer...
神でさえ 介することが
できなかったように｡
(先生)しかも なんか 文章
急に 達者になってますけど！
And you're suddenly writing like a pro!
(大五郎)もう うんざりだ｡
ｵﾚは 地面に向かって➡
I've had enough...
I spit on the ground and
light up a xxxboro.
ﾂﾊﾞを吐き捨て ﾏﾙﾎﾞﾛに火をつけた｡
(先生)何があった！
What happened?!
What happened over summer?!
この夏 いったい 何があった!?
大人の階段どころじゃないだろ！
This isn't a step towards being an adult!
大人のｴｽｶﾚｰﾀｰだろ！
It's a damn escalator!
(大五郎)人は環境に応じ
絶えず 変化せねば生きられない｡
Humans must change and adapt to their
environment in order to survive.
(先生)なんで ｺﾝﾄﾞﾙ!?
てか お前は変化しすぎだろう！
Why a condor?!
And you've changed way too much!
The man who refused to change and
stood still was practically a corpse.
お前のほうを観察したかったわ！
You should've been observed instead!
August 3rd.
(大五郎)ｵﾚは おふくろから➡
I casually tossed it a bottle of whiskey
I sniped from my mother.
くすねてきたｳｲｽｷｰを
無造作に ﾔﾂに投げつけた｡
ﾏﾀﾞｵ… 環境は変えてやった｡
Madao, I've changed your environment.
It's your turn to respond,
so why do you just lie there?
あとは お前の番だというのに
なぜ お前はそこで➡
ずっと 淀んだままでいる｡
いったい 何が不満だというのだ｡
What damaged you?
(先生)明らかだよね！
何が不満なのか 丸見えだよね！
Isn't that obvious?!
Madao didn't answer my question,
You can clearly see why he's unhappy!
instead it licked at the whiskey
with a sour look on its face.
This is what you meant by a
new member of the family?!
家族増えたって
そういう意味で!?
(大五郎)ﾏﾀﾞｵは いったい
いつになったら咲くのか…｡
When will Madao bloom?
天を仰ぐ ｵﾚを嘲笑うかのように
上空には ｺﾝﾄﾞﾙが旋回していた｡
I look up at the sky to see a condor
circling as though laughing at me.
(先生)だから
江戸に なんで ｺﾝﾄﾞﾙ!?
And why is there a condor in Edo?!
August 10th.
Ten days have passed since
we took in Madao.
ﾏﾀﾞｵを飼いはじめてから
10日 経ったが➡
相変わらず ﾔﾂの芽は出ない｡
It still hasn't sprouted.
いつものように ｵﾚは
おふくろからくすねたﾊﾞｰﾎﾞﾝを➡
As always, I casually toss it a bottle
of bourbon I swiped from my Mom.
無造作に ﾔﾂに投げつける｡
そこは もう
無造作じゃないとﾀﾞﾒなの？
Does it have to say "casually"?
かたくなに無造作なの？
Do you have to emphasize
that "casually" part?
(大五郎)最近 おふくろが
ﾏﾀﾞｵを気味悪がっている｡
Mom's been getting creeped
out by Madao recently.
どうやら ｵﾚが飼いはじめたのが
犬ではなく➡
It appears that she's realized I'm
keeping Madao and not a dog.
ﾏﾀﾞｵだということに
勘づきはじめているようだ｡
最初から丸わかりだろ！
最初から気味悪いよ！
That should have been obvious
from the beginning!
She was creeped out from the beginning!
女手ひとつで
ｵﾚを育ててくれた おふくろ｡
My Mom raised me on her own.
おふくろが 男を
信用しないようになったのは➡
I wonder when she stopped
trusting in men...?
いつからだったのだろうか｡
(先生)おふくろのことは
もういいよ！
Who cares about your Mom's story!
Just end this story!
いいから 早く締めて！
August 10th three years ago.
(先生)おい！
いいっつってんだろ!!
Hey! I said to stop!
なんで 日記で過去編!?
Why is there a flashback
arc in your journal?!
＜大五郎:あの日も うだるように
暑い日だったのを覚えている｡
I remember that it was
a blisteringly hot day.
おふくろの旦那…
つまり ｵﾚの親父も ﾏﾀﾞｵだった｡
My Mom's husband...
In other words, my old man,
was also a Madao.
親父は 腕のいい大工だったが➡
My old man was a skilled carpenter,
現場の事故で
腕が使えなくなってから➡
but after an accident left
his arms paralyzed,
働きもせずに 昼間から酒を飲み
博打を打つようになった｡
he stopped working and began drinking
and gambling during the day.
おふくろは いつでも
馬車馬のように働いては➡
My Mom always worked hard,
buy my old man would beat
her for not earning enough.
稼ぎが少ないと
親父に殴られていた｡
ｵﾚは
そんな親父の姿を見るのがｲﾔで➡
I couldn't stand the sight of my old man,
いつも日が暮れるまで
家に帰らなかった｡
so I never returned home
until the sun set.
働き疲れたおふくろを待ち
家路につく｡
I would wait for my exhausted
Mom before heading home.
それが ｵﾚの日課だった｡
That was my daily routine.
そんなﾏﾀﾞｵでも ｵﾚたちが
見限ることをしなかったのは➡
But we didn't abandon that Madao,
because of memories of long ago...
かつての遠い記憶…｡
We believed that he would return to
being a kind father, a kind husband.
優しかった父の
優しかった夫の姿が➡
いつか戻ってきてくれると
信じてのことだった｡
だが その日…＞
But that day...
We're home.
＜ｵﾚたちの淡い希望は➡
Our faint hopes
ｾﾐの声とともに 夏の空に消えた＞
vanished into the summer sky
with the cries of cicadas.
＜ｵﾚの頬に 雨が当たって流れた｡
Raindrops trickled down my cheek.
いつの間にか
ｵﾚは あるﾏﾀﾞｵの話を➡
Before I knew it, I had told the Madao
before me about the other Madao.
目の前のﾏﾀﾞｵに
長々と話し込んでいたらしい＞
すまねえ… 今の話は忘れてくれ｡
Sorry, forget about everything I just said.
Why did you help me...?
(長谷川)なぜ ｵﾚを…｡
Aren't you sick of seeing a Madao?
ﾏﾀﾞｵの姿なんて もう
見たくもねえんじゃねえのか？
お前も 母ちゃんも｡
Both you and your mother.
母ちゃん… 苦しませるだけ
なんじゃねえのか？
Aren't you making your mother suffer?
後悔してるのかもしれねえ｡
I might be feeling remorse...
親父が どん底に落ちちまったとき
支えてやれば➡
If only I had provided support for my
old man when he hit rock bottom...
おふくろは こんなことに
ならなかったんじゃねえかって｡
Then my Mom wouldn't
have suffered like this.
＜ その先の言葉は出なかった｡
I couldn't say anything more...
At some point, I may have seen
my old man in Madao.
ｵﾚは いつの間にか➡
親父とﾏﾀﾞｵの姿を
重ねていたのかもしれない｡
おふくろを苦しめてまで
ｵﾚは 何をしようとしているのか｡
What was I trying to accomplish
while making my Mom suffer?
あのときの忘れ物…｡
Was I trying to recover what
I'd once forgotten...?
今から取り戻せるとでも
思っているのだろうか｡
その日 ﾏﾀﾞｵは
ﾊﾞｰﾎﾞﾝに口をつけなかった＞
On that day, Madao didn't
touch its bourbon.
August 11th.
＜窓を叩く
けたたましい雨の音で➡
I awake to the sound of rain
pounding against the window.
ｵﾚは目を覚ました｡
どうやら 江戸に
台風が直撃しているらしい｡
It seems that a typhoon has hit Edo.
ｵﾚの足は
自然と犬小屋へ向かった｡
My legs led me to the doghouse.
しかし そこに
ﾏﾀﾞｵの姿はなかった＞
But Madao was nowhere to be found.
((長谷川:ﾏﾀﾞｵの姿なんて もう
見たくもねえんじゃねえのか？
Aren't you sick of seeing a Madao?
お前も 母ちゃんも))
Both you and your mother.
ｱﾝﾀ 何やってんの!!
What are you doing?!
この雨の中
どこへ行くっていうの!?
Where are you going in this rain?!
離せよ！ ただでさえ
酒びたりで弱りきってたんだ！
Let me go!
It's already weak from
drinking all that booze!
こんな雨の中じゃ
死んじまうよ ﾏﾀﾞｵ!!
Madao's going to die in this rain!
やっぱり…
ﾏﾀﾞｵだったんだね あれ…｡
So that was a Madao...
っげえよ！
ﾏﾀﾞｵなんかじゃねえよ!!
No!
It's not a Madao!
ｱｲﾂは… ｱｲﾂは…｡
It's... It's...
ｵﾚの友達だ！
My friend!
大五郎！
Daigoro!
《もう ｲﾔなんだ…
ｱｲﾂだけは 救ってやりたいんだ》
No more of this...
I have to save him!
August 12th.
I couldn't find Madao in the end.
＜結局
ﾏﾀﾞｵは見つかりませんでした｡
My head hurts and I can't write
as well as I did before.
なんだか頭が痛くて
前みたいに うまく書けません｡
I seem to have caught a cold.
ﾎﾞｸは
ｶｾﾞをひいてしまったようです｡
なんでだかわからないけど
お酒も飲んでないのに➡
I didn't drink any sake, but it's coming
out of my eyes for some reason.
目から お酒が出ました｡
ﾏﾀﾞｵみたいに…｡
Just like it did with Madao.
Is sake coming out of Madao's
eyes wherever he is?
ﾏﾀﾞｵも どこかで
目から お酒を出しているのかな？
When I thought of that, I couldn't
stop the sake from coming out.
そう思ったら お酒が
止まらなくなって困りました｡
そうしたら…＞
And then...
ﾏ… ﾏﾀﾞｵ｡
Ma-Madao...
Honestly...
まったく…
今度は 逃げないように➡
Next time keep an eye on
it so it won't escape.
ちゃんと見とくのよ｡
And also...
それから… ｺﾞﾎｯ ｺﾞﾎｯ！
ﾏﾀﾞｵ飼うなら 外は恥ずかしいから
家の中で飼いなさい｡ ｺﾞﾎｯ！
If you're going to keep a Madao, keep
it inside so we aren't embarrassed.
ｴｻも お酒じゃなくて
ちゃんとしたものあげるのよ｡
And feed it properly instead
of giving it alcohol.
ｺﾞﾎｯ ｺﾞﾎｯ！
Mom allowed me to keep Madao.
＜ お母さんは ﾏﾀﾞｵを飼うことを
許してくれました｡
Or maybe Mom felt the same way I did.
いや もしかしたら お母さんは➡
ﾎﾞｸと同じ気持だったのかも
しれません＞
ﾏﾀﾞｵ またお酒飲んだの？
Madao, were you drinking again?
いいや… もう飲まねえさ｡
No...
No more drinking for me.
August 20th.
＜ あれから ﾏﾀﾞｵは変わりました｡
Madao has changed since then.
He no longer drinks sake,
酒をきれいさっぱり断ち
お母さんのいない間➡
and he performs all kinds of
chores while Mom is out.
あらゆる家事をこなします｡
そして そのかたわら
求人雑誌を読みあさり➡
All while reading the classifieds.
お母さんは 最初は
ﾏﾀﾞｵって呼んでたけど➡
Mom called him Madao in the beginning,
最近は 長谷川さんと
呼ぶようになりました｡
but she's started to call
him Hasegawa-san.
Here, Hasegawa-san.
ﾏﾀﾞｵはﾏﾀﾞｵなのに なんでだろう｡
Madao is Madao, so why?
Ah, sorry about that. Thank you so much.
ﾎﾞｸには よくわかりません＞
I don't really get it.
August 25th.
When Madao went out for
errands that evening,
＜夕方 ﾏﾀﾞｵが
おつかいに行っているときに➡
お母さんが…＞
Mom asked...
Daigoro.
大五郎 お父さん欲しくない？
Would you like a father?
＜…と聞いてきました｡
That was her question.
I didn't understand what she meant,
聞いてる意味が
よくわからなかったので➡
ﾎﾞｸが聞き返したら
顔が真っ赤になっていました＞
so I asked her about it
and then her face turned red.
Well, it's nothing...
いや… なんでもない｡
I didn't understand,
＜ よくわからなかったので
夜 ﾏﾀﾞｵに聞いたら…＞
so I asked Madao that night...
知らねえよ｡
I wouldn't know.
I don't really get grownups.
＜大人は よくわかりません＞
August 26th.
It's finally the day for Madao to sprout.
＜ いよいよ
ﾏﾀﾞｵの芽の出る日がきました＞
今まで ありがとうございました｡
Thank you for everything you've done.
おかげさまで
どん底から ここまで➡
Thanks to you two, I've been able
to recover from hitting rock bottom.
はい上がることができました｡
I don't know how to show
my appreciation...
本当に２人には
なんと感謝を言っていいか…｡
あらあら 気が早いですよ｡
面接は これからでしょ｡
My, it's a little early for that.
You haven't gone to your interview yet.
There, your tie.
ほら ﾈｸﾀｲ｡
ｱﾊｯ すみません｡
Sorry about that.
たった１人しか合格できない
難関なんでしょう｡
Only one person will be
able to pass, right?
がんばってくださいね｡
吉報 待ってますから｡
Do your best.
We'll be waiting for the good news.
うん｡
はい！
Yes!
＜決戦に向かうﾏﾀﾞｵと
それを見送る お母さんは➡
As Madao headed off to battle
and Mom watched him go,
まるで お父さんと
お母さんみたいでした｡
they were like father and mother.
ﾏﾀﾞｵが お父さん｡
Madao as my father...
I tried to picture that, but
it felt weird so I stopped.
想像してみたけど なんだか
こそばゆかったので やめました＞
緊張してらっしゃるみたいですね｡
You seem to be nervous.
Huh? Oh, yes...
えっ!? あぁ… ええ｡
Since my return to a normal person
from being a Madao is riding on this.
なんせ ﾏﾀﾞｵから真人間への
復活が かかってるんで…｡
ああ そうなんですか｡
ﾎﾞｸと同じですね｡
Oh, is that so?
I'm the same.
Oh? You were also a Madao?
えっ!?
あなたもﾏﾀﾞｵだったんですか？
そうは見えませんが…｡
I couldn't tell...
いえね ｹｶﾞして職を失ってから
すっかり ｸﾞﾚてしまいまして｡
Well, I lost my job after an
injury and snapped...
妻や息子にも見放されて…｡
My wife and son gave up on me...
お恥ずかしい話 全部失ってから
大事なものに気づかされまして｡
I'm embarrassed to say that I didn't realize
what was important until I'd lost it all...
なんとか ここまで更生して➡
I managed to straighten myself up and
asked my wife if we could start over,
妻に やり直そうと
伝えたんですけど➡
but she told me to let her think about it.
考えさせてくれって
言われちゃいました｡
Well, it's okay.
まあ でも いいんです｡
今回 これに受かったら➡
I'll try again if I'm accepted here.
もう一度 ｱﾀｯｸしてみるんで…｡
ｲｽは ひとつしかないけど➡
There's only one opening, but let's both
do our best so we have no regrets.
お互い 悔いのないよう
がんばりましょうね｡
あの ひとつ聞いていいですか？
はい｡
Um... Can I ask you something?
Yes?
What's your son's name?
息子さんの名前
なんていうんですか？
August 27th.
＜ あれっきり
ﾏﾀﾞｵは戻りませんでした＞
Madao never came back.
きっと 面接落ちちゃったんだよ｡
He probably didn't pass the interview.
So he's too ashamed to face us.
それで
ﾎﾞｸらに あわせる顔がなくて｡
ﾊﾞｶだな ﾏﾀﾞｵ｡ そんなの
気を遣わなくてもいいのに｡
Madao's such an idiot.
He doesn't need to be so sensitive.
＜ お母さんは
何も言いませんでした｡
Mom didn't say anything.
ﾎﾞｸのせいで また
お母さん傷つけちゃったかな＞
Was Mom hurt again because of me?
August 29th.
＜ﾏﾀﾞｵと食事しました｡
We ate with Madao.
もう１人のﾏﾀﾞｵと｡
The other Madao.
ﾏﾀﾞｵは まるで
別人のように変わっていて➡
Madao had become a completely
different person.
ﾎﾞｸとお母さんに
何度も謝ったあと➡
After apologizing to Mom
and me over and over,
嬉しそうに 仕事が決まったことを
報告しました｡
he happily reported that he'd found a job.
面接会場で お酒を飲んで
大暴れした人がいたことを➡
He also cheerfully told
us about someone
who got drunk and made
a ruckus at the interview.
楽しそうにしゃべってました｡
お母さんも
とっても楽しそうでした＞
Mom also looked like
she was really happy.
よお そこのお二人さん｡
Yo, you two.
ｵｲﾗにちぃと
酒をわけちゃくれねえかい？
Could you spare me some sake?
大五郎 行くわよ｡
Daigoro, let's go.
大五郎？
Daigoro?
なんで…
もう飲まないって約束したのに｡
Why?
You promised never to drink again.
なんで…｡
試験がんばるって約束したのに｡
Why?
You promised to do your
best at the interview!
なんで なんで なんで！
Why...? Why...? Why...?!
酒がねえなら失せろ ｶﾞｷ｡
Get lost if you have no sake, kid.
もう ﾃﾒｴとはこれっきりだ｡
We're through.
Liar...
ｳｿつき｡
大五郎 もうやめなさい｡
Daigoro, that's enough.
行くわよ｡ これ以上
その人に関わるのはよしなさい｡
Let's go.
Don't bother with him any longer.
ｳｿつき！ ﾏﾀﾞｵ ﾎﾞｸは知ってるよ！
Liar!
Madao! I know!
大五郎！
どんなにｳｿついたって➡
Daigoro!
You may lie!
どんなに
酔っ払ったふりしたって➡
You may pretend to be drunk!
どんなにみんなが
ﾏﾀﾞｵを悪く言ったって ﾎﾞｸは…｡
Everybody may badmouth you!
I know...
ﾏﾀﾞｵは ﾏﾀﾞｵなんかじゃない！
I know that Madao is no Madao!
ﾎﾞｸの忘れ物を取り戻してくれた！
You brought back what
I'd once forgotten!
誰よりも優しい立派な侍だって…｡
You're the nicest, best samurai!
ﾎﾞｸ 忘れないから
絶対 忘れないから！
I won't forget!
I'll never forget!
Never!
絶対！
What's with all the noise?
なんじゃ やかましいのう｡
あれ 長谷川さん
ｱﾝﾀ戻ってきたのかい｡
Oh? Hasegawa-san.
You're back?
おっ ちぃともらうよ｡
I'll have a bit.
What the hell?!
何じゃこりゃ？
み 水じゃねえか！
I-Isn't this water?!
酒も仕事もいらねえよ｡
I don't need beer or work...
ｵﾚはもう十分
いろんなもんもらったからよ｡
I've already received enough...
大五郎…
父ちゃん母ちゃんと 幸せにな｡
Daigoro, be happy with
your Mom and dad.
＜ そう ﾎﾞｸは知っていました｡
Yes, I knew.
ﾏﾀﾞｵは もう
とっくに咲いているって＞
Madao had already bloomed long ago...
大五郎君 ごめん｡
Daigoro-kun...
Forgive me...
もう観察日記っていうか➡
That was no observation journal...
ほとんど小説だったけどよかった｡
It was practically a novel...
But it was wonderful!
すごくよかった！
みんな大五郎君に拍手！
Magnificent!
Everybody give Daigoro some applause!
(拍手)
[Cast]
ん？ あれ まだ続いてんの？
Huh?
[Madao: Taizo Hasegawa]
It's still going?
[Me: Daigoro Kitaouji]
あっ
ｴﾝﾄﾞﾛｰﾙまであるんだ すごいね｡
Oh, there's even a credit roll.
[Mom: Satsuki Kitaouji]
[Dad: Daisuke Kitaouji]
Amazing, it's like a movie.
映画みたいだね｡
いや すばらしかった｡
[Old Man at Park: Isoroku Yadonashi]
Man, that was great.
[Narration]
[Daigoro Kitaouji]
Everyone, one more round
of applause for Daigoro!
[Directed / Script by]
みんなもう一度 大五郎君に拍手！
(拍手)
[Directed / Script by]
[Mom]
えっ…｡
Huh?
お母さんが書いたんかいっ！
Your mother wrote this?!
[Temple School]
Do your own homework!!
The next episode...
"Radio Exercises are Socials
for Boys and Girls."
[I think we're going to forget the fact it's winter again
next week and do an episode about radio exercises.]
[Actually, it's a two-parter. In part one, a journalist
seriously looks into the Anti-Foreigner Faction battle.]
[See you next time.]